[SPEAKER_00]: So, any ideas, Prabhupāda, to sum up?
[SPEAKER_04]: Maybe about the sankhāras and the difference between sankhāras and cetanā.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what do you think is the difference?
[SPEAKER_04]: Saṅkharas are involved with avijja.
[SPEAKER_04]: Cetanas are more like free from avijja.
[SPEAKER_00]: But isn't... can you have cetanā without it being sankhāra?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because sankhāra just means activity or doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how can you have intention or choice without it being an activity?
[SPEAKER_04]: From my point of view, I cannot step outside of my experience as a whole and see how would it be without avijjā.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, but what do you think it... like, what do you have to remove?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, everybody recognizes that they have sankhāras in their experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, whether that's chetan or not, we can put that aside, but what do you need to remove in order for... Well, can we... but are we on the same page about what we are talking about when I used to do a sankhāra to begin with?
[SPEAKER_03]: Right.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, I guess we should verify that first.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, usually, it's understood as like volitional formations or various kinds of translations that people have come up with and it usually feels to people, I think, like it's it's something that's not really my control.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's something that gets removed kind of indirectly by this practice that I do that at some point
[SPEAKER_00]: It gets rid of the ignorance and somehow also gets rid of the saṅkharas.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, eh... it's actually something that you are active... like it's a doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Saṅkhara means doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, eh... in kind of a...
[SPEAKER_00]: I guess, eh... these are not like philosophical terms that the Buddha was using with some kind of grandiose significance.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's if you... if you read like Vedic writings and stuff, when they...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in the use of the word saṅkhara, they were referring it to the stuff that they would do, like rituals, like things that they would organize, play out, kind of do, and not as some kind of, I don't know, energies or something.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, saṅkharas have to be seen in the practical sense of things that you are doing, things that you're responsible for.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so, from that point of view, what would you have to remove to fix the problem with santhāras, basically?
[SPEAKER_00]: Can you just step out of saṅkharas from the very beginning?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what is the thing that you have to do then?
[SPEAKER_04]: Understand what saṅkhara are.
[SPEAKER_04]: Right, but even before that?
[SPEAKER_02]: In other words, you have to recognize, if you think you can kind of avoid them from the very beginning, you probably have a misconception of what saṅkharas are.
[SPEAKER_02]: All you can do is cultivate certain kinds of saṅkharas.
[SPEAKER_02]: that don't fuel ignorance.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you have no choice but to do things, in other words.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, certain doings will, at least, not fuel your ignorance further.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's the first step.
[SPEAKER_02]: You have to recognize that there are wholesome saṅkharas and unwholesome saṅkharas.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that, yeah, so that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the practice of virtue.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, on the basis of that,
[SPEAKER_00]: You can get to understand what the cessation of sankhāras actually is.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, when you have established yourself in good sankhāras, quote-unquote, good actions, then you can understand the cessation of action altogether.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's the real gist of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like... it's not that you remove ignorance and then you are left... you kind of go from sankhāras to cetanā.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, as the Buddha said, cetanā is kamma as well.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, and he also said cessation of suffering is cessation of kamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: In other words, cessation of cetanā as well.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, eh... more accurately speaking, eh... cessation of suffering is the cessation of all activities or all doings or all intentions as well.
[SPEAKER_02]: And sometimes even the Buddha would say that eh... there is eh...
[SPEAKER_02]: Intention, when there is cetanā, by body, speech and mind, as a result of that, suffering arises.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's the cessation of all of that, that constitutes actual freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: You cannot have sankhāras or cetanā, and at the same time, not have suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, of course, now then, the thing is, it's not a... like, it can sound as if...
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, so, cessation of all action probably will sound to most people as some kind of a exotic state of just unconsciousness or something.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, it's something that you have to actually develop.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's... and it's also...
[SPEAKER_02]: Not something that happens to you, it's something that you understand.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, literally, the word understanding refers to knowing something for yourself and knowing how you got there.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not just, oh, I got this experience where there was no doer, no sense of self, but, okay, but what do you actually understand there?
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what really matters.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, how then would you
[SPEAKER_03]: Or let's say, first of all, what is the ignorance as a result of which there are saṅkharas automatically?
[SPEAKER_03]: What are you most acutely not aware of?
[SPEAKER_02]: Instead of just tell the five aggregates or some kind of theoretical thing, what are you most acutely not aware of because of which you have saṅkharas?
[SPEAKER_04]: Simultaneity.
[SPEAKER_04]: There's something that undermines my attention itself.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, that would be all the practice, I think.
[SPEAKER_02]: You could put it that way, but even before you can go in that direction, there's something more, even more acute, that you need to recognize.
[SPEAKER_02]: Something very simple.
[SPEAKER_03]: There's a characteristic of saṅkharas that's pretty much... like, it's the only reason why they can be there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Take responsibility for my action.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes, but how would you... what is the precondition for you to take responsibility for an action?
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a very simple answer.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a precept.
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: Very, very, very direct thing.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's almost like a silly kind of question in a way, but you realize actually it's not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just be aware of myself.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, yeah, be aware that you're doing something to begin with.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because that's the... like, it's not some unawareness of something.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, like, you can come up with all sorts of explanations of unawareness of three characteristics and this and that.
[SPEAKER_03]: But really, most primarily, when it comes to saṅkharas, you're unaware of them to begin with.
[SPEAKER_03]: In other words, you don't recognize that you're actually doing that thing.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, yes, as you said, you... the first step to doing anything about it would be taking responsibility.
[SPEAKER_03]: But in order to take responsibility for your action, you need to know that it is actually an action.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it's not going to feel like that initially.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, eh... because what we're talking about here is not really just, eh...
[SPEAKER_02]: I can't hold some saṅkharas by body and speech, because, as we said, that would have to be abandoned beforehand.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, these are now things that, having developed the good saṅkharas, as I said before, to replace the bad saṅkharas, you wouldn't even be aware that those saṅkharas are things that you're doing.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, which includes mental action.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, most primarily, it converges at that point, basically, because even when somebody goes into complete state of just vegetable or something, that's the part that can never go away.
[SPEAKER_02]: On some level, if you are alive,
[SPEAKER_05]: There is some degree of activity.
[SPEAKER_05]: And that's actually already a good contemplation, to just ask yourself, like, mental action.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, instead of just agreeing, oh yeah, there's body, speech and mind, so there must be mental action.
[SPEAKER_05]: But, can I make a list of things that I've been mentally doing, mentally doing in the
[SPEAKER_05]: It's actually very... it's a very common thing that people would think that the daydreaming kind of happens by itself or something.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then they kind of need to shut it down by watching their breath or something.
[SPEAKER_02]: And actually, all that is rooted in just not seeing that that is something that you're doing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if I...
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't know, if you're jumping, and then you want to stop jumping,
[SPEAKER_02]: Do you have to watch your breath in order to stop jumping?
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: You stop jumping.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the same thing is on the mental level, exactly the same principle, but because the person hasn't developed themselves sufficiently in restraining the actions of body and speech, and the action of the mind feels like it's nebulous thing that almost doesn't exist.
[SPEAKER_00]: Some people would even say that their their thoughts are not real or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: So,
[SPEAKER_03]: It's actually, like, that's the first step.
[SPEAKER_03]: You need to actually recognize, oh, I am actually doing this.
[SPEAKER_02]: And, eh... all of the prerequisites of the graduate training are geared towards making that apparent.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, eh... you know, having developed yourself in the precepts and sensory strength and all these things, when you're in seclusion, eh... it would become very hard to ignore
[SPEAKER_02]: Obviously for a while, not just like one day or something.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if that becomes your mode of your lifestyle, it would be very hard not to become aware that the daydreaming is actually something that you're doing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because even if in the beginning it feels like it's coming by itself,
[SPEAKER_02]: Once you've been left alone for a while and haven't been distracting yourself, you will start to realize, actually, I am...
[SPEAKER_02]: I am kind of fuel... actively fueling this and... and... when it stops, I restart it and I... and I kind of...
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm...
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm literally responsible for it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And, eh... then you will start to see, oh, actually, that is a saṅkhara, that it was arising solely because I was ignorant of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And further... furthermore,
[SPEAKER_03]: Also, if you want to take the textbook definition, it's also ignorance of the Four Noble Truths.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, all sankhāras, ultimately, kind of, even if it's not a coarse kind, it's going to be coming out of craving.
[SPEAKER_03]: And so, not seeing that it is actually painful, not seeing that it is actually... like, you project it onto
[SPEAKER_02]: The objective of your daydreaming, like the thing I want to get, or the thing I want to get rid of, or whatever, and you kind of carry the view that that's the... like not having accomplished that, is the reason for your pain.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ignoring the fact that it's the craving, right then and there, that's actually causing the pain.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, not seeing that craving is suffering, gives rise to that saṅkhara, automatically.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it doesn't have to be that, oh, I believe that I have to solve this problem or something.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just ignoring the fact that it's the craving
[SPEAKER_02]: First of all, that the craving is there.
[SPEAKER_02]: And second of all, that it's the craving that is the actual root of suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: Automatically, you give rise to sankhāras.
[SPEAKER_02]: You try to... Why?
[SPEAKER_02]: You're trying to resolve the pain.
[SPEAKER_03]: Which, if you realize, oh, actually, it's the craving to resolve the pain, not the pain.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's the suffering.
[SPEAKER_03]: What purpose would any effort of doing, eh... have?
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that's why cessation of saṅkharas, again, is not a mystical thing.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's literally just when you don't have any further need to get rid of pain or pursue pleasure.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's as concrete as that, because every saṅkhara converges around that, converges around not wanting to endure whatever is there.
[SPEAKER_05]: And so, all the actions that were previously tainted by craving, by body, speech and mind, would cease.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, yeah, action as a phenomenon in of itself, that would have to cease as well, because...
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, that's why even in the suttas you wouldn't see actually a definition of saying that an arahant
[SPEAKER_02]: kind of has a few or five attributes or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that would mean saying that they still have saṅkharas.
[SPEAKER_00]: And nibbāna is a cessation of saṅkharas itself, undefined.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that would be a contradiction.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then you realize, so how can you have
[SPEAKER_03]: That's when you realize that it's a very literal statement when the Buddha says that it's not... that it's only cetanā that is khandhā.
[SPEAKER_03]: You think, oh yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_02]: But no, it means that physical movements, verbal movements, even mental movements, in and of themselves, are not what khandhā is.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the
[SPEAKER_02]: Intending, the kind of directing or inclining towards things, that is the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_03]: If there is no inclining... Actually, I think there's a sutta that says, eh...
[SPEAKER_03]: When one is dependent, one is moved.
[SPEAKER_02]: When one is moved, one inclines.
[SPEAKER_02]: And as a result of inclining,
[SPEAKER_02]: There is coming and going.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And with coming and going, there is sickness, aging, death.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, birth, sickness, aging, death.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's that kind of... it's as simple as that.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's cetanā.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not just like I decide to do something and I kind of manifest it out into the world.
[SPEAKER_02]: Initially, of course, it's going to feel like that.
[SPEAKER_03]: And when you start keeping the precepts and restraining your actions,
[SPEAKER_03]: You're going to start to see that that was kind of the very last outpour of the river, like the last part, basically.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it's really just, eh... inclining towards something, having that kind of direction, directionality in your experience.
[SPEAKER_03]: And when ignorance is abandoned, again, in the very concrete terms, when there's pleasure,
[SPEAKER_02]: And there is no directionality, no inclining towards needing to have more of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, there's no cetanā.
[SPEAKER_02]: If there's no inclining towards needing to have less pain, there's no cetanā.
[SPEAKER_03]: Then, you could say, okay, well, it's only to the extent that the
[SPEAKER_03]: Nothing that you would do would be rooted in... That's factually when you would have no self.
[SPEAKER_03]: There's a sense of an outside kind of thing that's trying to puppet stuff around to kind of get what it wants.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, see, you arrive at it indirectly, through that non-inclination, rather than, like, deciding beforehand that you will deny your sense of control, rooted in your sense of control, that just wants to get rid of things.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's... that sense of self, that sense of I, is a side effect
[SPEAKER_00]: of that inclination to control things, rather than being some kind of metaphysical entity that you destroy or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, that's where you need to look for the saṅkharas, in relation to pleasure and pain, because that's where the activation, where the inclination comes to be.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, in relation to the things that you want to do, that your mind is pressured to do, that's where you calm the saṅkharas, not in relation to kind of everywhere, nowhere.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's when you have contained yourself by the precepts, you will naturally, whether you like it or not, unless you're distracting yourself with some kind of oblivion practice,
[SPEAKER_02]: You will start to notice that your mind is inclining towards certain things.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's inevitable.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's where you need to then start understanding, okay, how do I cut this off at the root, rather than replacing it with something else, which is going to be another activity, or kind of thinking to counter it, or just looking away
[SPEAKER_00]: All of those are going to be activities.
[SPEAKER_03]: Instead, you need to find how do I go to the very root of this whole inclination, this whole movement of just trying.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not trying to do something, just trying as a thing in itself.
[SPEAKER_03]: How do I cut that off?
[SPEAKER_03]: And, well, it's exactly through what you said initially.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's through the understanding of dependent origination, quote-unquote.
[SPEAKER_02]: By recognizing with this, this is, you kind of remove any space because of which you could assume that you can do something about it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because all you see is this and this other thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, where is the space for me to interfere in between?
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's why it's so important to see it as a simultaneous presence of two things, because for as long as it's like observing the one thing coming, and then the next one, and then the next one, it's going to be your sense of self that's observing that.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that observation in and of itself is an activity, no matter how subtle it feels, like you thinking that you're seeing the sequence of mind moments coming and going.
[SPEAKER_02]: That is an activity.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, we gave one example of sankhāras, which is on a practical level, which would be daydreaming, let's say, and thinking coarse, sensual thoughts, perverse thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what would be another... can we come up with other examples of... so that it doesn't feel like an abstract thing, those sankhāras that you would be doing?
[SPEAKER_00]: Even when you are already virtuous and established in a certain boundary of conduct.
[SPEAKER_01]: Wanting something.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what would be the solution to that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Can you just cash in wanting?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's become what I want now.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you have to start like that, of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: Otherwise, you won't... you won't try and you will just fall into some sort of abstract idea of, okay, I just don't want anything and that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, you have to start with an activity.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, I want to solve this because there's a problem here.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, how... so what would be the solution?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, how do you... Yeah, I think it's more, kind of, what you say, like, more or less, before, is, like, instead of, kind of, myself doing it, like, more, like, discerning that, actually, whether I like it or not, I cannot want things to be otherwise than they already are, because it's just me interfering with
[SPEAKER_01]: What determines what I can interfere with, which is kind of a contradiction in itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it that, like, what would you practically discern?
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's say, you have wanting of some even neutral kind.
[SPEAKER_02]: How do you see that you cannot interfere?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, again, just telling yourself, like, I cannot interfere, it might be accurate, but unless you actually see
[SPEAKER_03]: The fact that, like, you put... you see it in such a way that even if you wanted to interfere, you see that you can't.
[SPEAKER_02]: How are you able to see that way?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you kind of have to develop the kind of recognitions that...
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, one of the kind of foundation of mindfulness, for example, like just organizing that, well,
[SPEAKER_01]: The body is like the basis on which I can act and I can never step outside of that, regardless.
[SPEAKER_01]: And just like, not like putting it in the front, like, just like looking at looking at that, but just more recognizing, like, my whole experience is defined by that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I can never, like, actually get out of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: As you said at the beginning, Patrick, like, say, like,
[SPEAKER_01]: My experience as a whole is defined by that, regardless.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I'm just keeping that in mind, but let it sink.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not, like, over-rationalizing it, but, like, just let it pervade, so to say.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you basically have to recognize that even if you go and, like, you don't deny that whatever it is your mind wants to do, that you could do it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because that would be kind of just, um...
[SPEAKER_02]: Wishful thinking, in a way.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, it's like, there is a possibility there.
[SPEAKER_03]: But the fact is, even if I were to actually go and do it, would I ever step outside of this foundation?
[SPEAKER_03]: Actually, you realize, no.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, from that perspective,
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, you become clear.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, even when I... let's say you take the foundation of feeling.
[SPEAKER_03]: Even when I actually went, and in the past, and engaged with sensuality, and pursued this, and got angry with people, and got into fights and stuff, did I ever actually step outside of that feeling that initially got me to act?
[SPEAKER_03]: And you realize, actually, no.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's, it's... pretty much every time, it actually even got worse.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, if you just recognize that, you see, okay, yes, I could act, like, I could go and do this, whatever, but, from this perspective, I'm not actually moving anywhere.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's when it ceases to be a saṅkhara.
[SPEAKER_03]: I think we spoke about that at some point.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, it's a saṅkhara not because of the kind of movement of your arms or something.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a saṅkhara because there's that assumption that you are actually going somewhere else.
[SPEAKER_03]: Whereas you realize, actually, no, there's anything that's done would have to remain exactly on the same level as where I started from.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, even if you were to go and do it, you don't deny that there is that possibility.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's like, as far as you...
[SPEAKER_03]: Possibly be able to go.
[SPEAKER_03]: You will never be able to step outside.
[SPEAKER_03]: You will never actually be able to go anywhere.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's where that sutta, where the Buddha says, like, the the world is to be known within the confines of this phalanx-long body, and it's it's the cessation of the world is found there as well.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, in other words,
[SPEAKER_02]: There is nothing outside of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And anywhere that you would go, you still remain in that same body.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like... and when you... as you said before, when you're daydreaming, when you're having kind of unwholesome thoughts even about this or that, instead of just
[SPEAKER_03]: Replacing it with another kind of daydreaming, because that's a funny thing, like, you would kind of imply that if I'm focusing on some specific object, magically, that isn't daydreaming anymore, but actually, just because it's kind of more moving less or something, but it's exactly still the same assumption of movement, the same assumption of going somewhere else.
[SPEAKER_02]: Instead,
[SPEAKER_02]: You go the other way, and you recognize, you undermine the whole possibility, and you see, it doesn't matter what I do, it doesn't matter what I attend to, it doesn't matter whether I sit, stand, walk, or lie down, I'm not actually going anywhere.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's, that's, eh... in a way, that's, eh... probably even in a pleasant recognition, especially if you're not developed in virtue, because it's like being confined, and realizing, like, well,
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, again, like, it's not even a matter of I am deciding to calm my mind or something.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like, even if I were to ignore this and go back, or whatever, I won't ever...
[SPEAKER_05]: I won't ever actually be able to get outside of this.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, you're properly cornered, basically.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, at the same time, it is also the most relieving thing of all, because you realize, like,
[SPEAKER_03]: Also, I don't even have to do what I assumed the practice was.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, go here, and do this, and think about this, and remove this, or do that.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, it's actually the other direction.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's recognizing that you can't even change anything, even if you want to.
[SPEAKER_02]: But before that, in order to arrive at that point, like I said before, you need to have tried and strived and done things on that level of virtue, restraint and stuff, because otherwise you would just be misconceiving what saṅkharas are based on
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever assumption can be used, you carry, and you won't be seeing it concreting in that yoniso sense.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, right here, what am I actually doing?
[SPEAKER_02]: You instead be imposing whatever you read, or heard, or thought, or reflected saṅkharas are into your experience, and then that's... anything that comes out of that is just going to be another saṅkhara.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think even, yeah, actually, we'll give you a simile of, like, um...
[SPEAKER_00]: When he referred to... that's the word that people translate as, like, how to stop thinking.
[SPEAKER_00]: Majjhima 20.
[SPEAKER_00]: He said, eh... how do you calm the activity, the saṅkhara, of thinking.
[SPEAKER_02]: And he said, eh... it's like a person who's running, recognizes, why am I running?
[SPEAKER_02]: Why if I walk?
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, after walking for a while, they recognize, why am I walking?
[SPEAKER_02]: Why do I stand?
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, it goes all the way down to, okay, so why am I sitting?
[SPEAKER_03]: Let me lie down.
[SPEAKER_03]: Then, you realize the whole principle there is that the saṅkhara is something that the person becomes aware of, like they were previously unaware of.
[SPEAKER_02]: They weren't realizing it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Once they recognize it, they're able to kind of
[SPEAKER_02]: If you don't recognize it, if you don't see exactly what it is that
[SPEAKER_02]: If you don't see that the whole thing is actually coming from you, it's not being imposed by your mind, kind of working on its own or something.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's you choosing to engage with these things that present themselves.
[SPEAKER_02]: And nobody else can come in between.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's you alone.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you don't see that, anything you try to do is still going to be within the same cragons, in ignorance as well, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what you say, like, now is like, as long as someone doesn't recognize, like, this principle, like, to the full extent, he basically didn't take dukkha responsibility fully, yes?
[SPEAKER_01]: Still, kind of, assume that something happened.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's... like, that is why it is fully... like, nothing can... like, fully universal.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if it were that something you kind of concoct and it just came up, you develop this thing and then it sort of stays there for a while, inherently, that's going to be impermanent.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if it's you recognizing, oh, I was actually doing this stuff.
[SPEAKER_02]: Let me now stop.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, who can actually...
[SPEAKER_02]: Even if, like, let's say you were running and somebody puts a gun to your head and says, start running again.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, he can't actually force you to run.
[SPEAKER_02]: It would be you who would make a choice not to die and run instead.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, nobody can force you to do anything.
[SPEAKER_03]: And in the same way, nobody can force you to engage or to do saṅkharas.
[SPEAKER_03]: Nobody can force you to have craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not even Mara, as the Sutta said, like, when he was trying to provoke the Buddha, because he said, well, I own the eye, I own the ear, I own the... all of the six senses.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then the Buddha said, yes, that's true.
[SPEAKER_03]: But...
[SPEAKER_03]: He didn't say, he didn't say, oh, you're wrong about that.
[SPEAKER_03]: He said, no, that's factually correct.
[SPEAKER_03]: But there is an escape from that, which you don't understand.
[SPEAKER_05]: Now, is taking responsibility an activity?
[SPEAKER_04]: It's a thought.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, I think, yes.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, is that something that, in the end, can also go to the cessation of saṅkhara?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, because I think there is a difference in between, like, taking responsibility
[SPEAKER_00]: Taking already implies something you did.
[SPEAKER_03]: The verb taking.
[SPEAKER_03]: But if you realize, well, I am responsible, like the same principle, I am responsible even if I don't want to be responsible, then it's not you taking responsibility.
[SPEAKER_02]: And ironically, that recognition
[SPEAKER_02]: It frees you from the burden of responsibility.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because the only reason responsibility was a burden is because you thought, you still implied that it was possible to avoid it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's the principle with everything.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, you don't actually fix what you think the problem is.
[SPEAKER_02]: You simply realize that there was no need to fix it in the first place.
[SPEAKER_00]: In terms of getting rid of pain and getting rid of... or pursuing pleasure, of course, initially, like I said, it is a problem if you're engaging in certain actions, like breaking the precept, because as much as you might want to tell yourself, through fancy ideas, that you can do that without craving, you are actually taking up the entire spectrum of experience just by doing any of those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what would be another very...
[SPEAKER_00]: There's a pertinent saṅkhara that would be there when you give up, let's say, the obvious bad saṅkharas of... let's say you... the person is taking the precepts and bodily, verbally and even mentally, they don't engage with sensuality, aversion or distraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: That, of course, doesn't mean that they're pure already, because then it would take one day to turn around.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what is left there?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's still not quite reined in.
[SPEAKER_01]: Isn't it like the same principle?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, I am doing all this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, I am the one, like, holding this precept, holding this virtue, holding this sense-restraint, and there will be a result out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, I'm expecting these things.
[SPEAKER_03]: That is... that is the... what it kind of boils down to.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, more specifically, what... what is the kind of... what would be the thing that you're still doing when, merely having restrained yourself from coarse behaviors, you'd still be kind of...
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, there would be hindrances, for example.
[SPEAKER_05]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_05]: Or just the expectation that there's still something to get that you do not have.
[SPEAKER_05]: Right, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_05]: But what is it that you would be trying to get that you don't have?
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, you think that you can get peace if the feeling which is not present is otherwise, for example.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's basically, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, then, you realize
[SPEAKER_03]: Or still, you would still carry the assumption that the solution to all of this is to replace whatever pressure is there with something else.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And for that reason alone, you're suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like it's the craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not what you thought you had to resolve.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's always the craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why the Buddha said, even in the, like in the satipaṭṭhāna contemplation,
[SPEAKER_02]: He said, when there's a mind with greed, he said, you know the mind of greed is a mind with greed.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it says, through that practice, you avoid disengaged, not taking up anything in the world.
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't say that he replaces the mind of greed with something else.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, again, that would be taking it up.
[SPEAKER_02]: You abandon the mind of greed simply to the extent that you don't act out of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: But then, now, if you also carry the opposite activity of still, to some tiny extent, expecting that it shouldn't be there...
[SPEAKER_02]: Which is part of the greed, actually.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: That partakes in the same thing.
[SPEAKER_03]: And, ironically, then, through the craving... Like, it's because of the craving that that greed is there.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, by fueling the craving, whether it's towards or against, you're fueling the basis for greed.
[SPEAKER_02]: And so, even if you did, actually,
[SPEAKER_02]: Get rid of it somehow, through whatever means.
[SPEAKER_02]: The fact that you still cultivated craving, that's precisely what's going to make it arise again.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even if, oh, you feel victorious or whatever, because you succeeded in removing it.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's still pretty much the same principle of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, I just have this thing, push it away with something better, and feel satisfied as a result of that.
[SPEAKER_02]: It is quite a hard thing for people to accept, because all their views are about countering and finding a quick solution for the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you don't realize, actually, that middle way that the Buddha described is a much more subtle thing than just like, oh, don't be too kind of ascetic and don't be too indulgent either.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of course, that's the
[SPEAKER_00]: Broad kind of principle that you'd be able to recognize externally, but even that...
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the Buddha said... well, some of his disciples would be eating once every three days, and the other ones would be eating food from the king every day.
[SPEAKER_00]: So... and wearing silk robe and whatnot.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, even on that level, you can't quite say that it's just a external, predefined type of conduct.
[SPEAKER_03]: It is...
[SPEAKER_03]: Most securely, on that internal level, whether you kind of engage with the bad saṅkharas, or you engage with the good ones.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which is, the good saṅkhara is the saṅkhara of trying to get, basically trying to get rid of your sensuality, trying to get rid of your aversion, through that sense of like, I want something else, I want this to go away.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, which eventually also has to cease.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So that's the, that's the
[SPEAKER_00]: All of the times the Buddha would describe, like, oh, the tuning of the strings, how do you cross the flood?
[SPEAKER_02]: It's by not pushing forward, by not standing still.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, all of that converges around that principle.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, you push forward, well...
[SPEAKER_03]: Initially, let's say, you're not even pushing forward.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're just letting it carry you away.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's your initial state of everybody as a householder.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just give in.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just go with the flow.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just go with it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, of course, unless you fight it, you won't be able to establish the basis for the middle way, which is the precepts.
[SPEAKER_03]: But at a certain point, you have to realize, wait, now I need to learn how to drop this without going back to just not doing anything at all and letting the flood carry me.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, without doing either, that's the cessation of suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's basically what sīlavata paramāsa is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, it's not a thing that's just hidden somewhere in your subconscious.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is like something that will actually be present quite frequently.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like that tendency to kind of literally hold on to the sense of duty, of like, I need to get rid of this, I need to kind of... just going beyond
[SPEAKER_03]: You were at the right point.
[SPEAKER_03]: You just gave up.
[SPEAKER_03]: You stopped engaging with sensuality, but you keep carrying it further into, like, out of just that sense of duty.
[SPEAKER_03]: It doesn't have to be anything specific.
[SPEAKER_05]: That momentum has to cease as well, basically.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not discerning that, actually, I already did what I had to do, and then I just keep winding myself up by assuming that there's something more and then overlooking.
[SPEAKER_03]: Just by overlooking the fact that, oh, I was actually right where I had to be, then you just keep going elsewhere.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, because probably it felt sort of dissatisfying or unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: I think there's more to be done.
[SPEAKER_03]: Rather than to just... And that goes back to what I said.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's like, any sense of what you might assume is what you need to resolve,
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just going to be a distraction from what the actual problem is, which is, right now, I'm craving against something.
[SPEAKER_02]: If there's any sense of, like, oh, doubt and asking myself, oh, what is it?
[SPEAKER_02]: What is it?
[SPEAKER_02]: And feeling overwhelmed or something.
[SPEAKER_02]: All of that can only be because I'm overlooking something that should, in a way, be obvious.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not because of the kind of built-up ignorance, but you realize, actually, it's right there.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not as, kind of, clearly defined as what I'm used to seeing, like objects out there in the world.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it is, factually, I am feeling like this.
[SPEAKER_02]: If somebody were to come and ask me, like, how do you feel?
[SPEAKER_02]: You would give the answer.
[SPEAKER_02]: And right there, in relation to that ambiguous feeling, you are trying to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: There cannot be anything else that causes you suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's just drilling that in, because you may recognize it for a moment, but then the assumption will set back in, and you will continue then trying to...
[SPEAKER_02]: Find the answer and resolve it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And somehow, through different ways, it's not always going to be the same solution that you're going to be striving for.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the common thread is you're looking for something.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's the problem.
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't matter whether you incline up, down, left, right, front or back.
[SPEAKER_02]: The point is that inclination, in and of itself, is what causes birth, aging, death, all of what I said before.